Guide to the Jane Porter Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jane Porter collection
1805-1848
GEN MSS 265
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(2 boxes)
Contains letters from Porter to various people, including Sir James Bland Burges, Dominic Paul Colnaghi, Mrs. S. C. Hall, James Justinian Morier, Thomas Joseph Pettigrew, and Owen Rees; holograph version of Porter's "The Pastor's Fire Side"; and proofs for Porter's "Thaddeus of Warsaw."
Porter, Jane, 1776-1850
Porter, Jane, 1776-1850 ( Pastor's fire-side)
Porter, Jane, 1776-1850 ( Thaddeus of Warsaw)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Jane Porter, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Authors, English -- Archives; Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824; Colnaghi, Dominic Charles, 1790-1879; Hall, S. C., Mrs., 1800-1881; Morier, James Justinian, 1780?-1849; Pettigrew, Thomas Joseph, 1791-1865; Porter, Jane, 1776-1850; Rees, Owen, 1770-1837
- Letters from Jane Porter, n.d.; Series I
  - ALS to Lady Brydges, London (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Gift, 1953.
  - AN in the third person, to Sir James Bland Burges, Upper Berkeley Street, [London], May 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Thanking him for a copy of his "Dramas, and the Dragon Knight." Gift, 1934.
  - ALS (fragment) to Mrs. Colbot, [1805?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Paper watermarked 1805. Gift, 1957.
  - ALS to Thomas Collier, Hyde Park North, London, 1844 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2 ALS to Dominic Paul Colnaghi, 1848, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gift, 1957.
  - ALS to Anna Maria Hall, London, [1834?] Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ALS to Anna Maria Hall, London, 1835 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Purchase, 1956.
  - AL (in third person) to editor of Literary Gazette, London, 1826 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ALS to James Morier, Bristol, 1845 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift.
  - AL (in third person) to Mr. Ogle, London, [1838] Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ALS to Thomas Joseph Pettigrew, Esher, 1829 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ALS to Owen Rees, Esher, [1827] Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AN in the third person to J. Rickerby, Bristol, [1845] Mar 8
    Purchase, 1937.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Box 2, folder 19
  - 7 ALS to George [Henry] Vertue, Jr., Bristol, England, 1844-45
  - ALS (in third person) to Mr. and Mrs. Samuel Wilson, Shirley Park, 1838 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Purchase, 1957.
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Hyde Park Place, London (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Removed from: Literary History of England by Margaret Oliphant (London, 1882).
  - AL (fragments), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Accompanied by ink wash drawing of a nun. Gift, 1956.
- Writings of Jane Porter, 1845 Nov; Series II
  - "The Pastor's Fire Side," Bristol, 1845 Nov (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Autograph manuscript dedication and introductory material to a new illustrated edition. Purchase, 1956.
  - "Thaddeus of Warsaw"
    - Five original colored drawings by Edward Borbould, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Page proofs, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      In volume. For the revised and illustrated edition of her novel published by George Vertue. Heavily corrected and rewritten by Porter. Pages 406-434, appendix, and index are entirely in Porter's hand. Purchase, 1937.